



<u>www.LondonResearchInternational.com</u>



London

NATIONALITY: South Africa

SUMMARY

I am an agricultural economist with a Masters degree in agricultural economics and with more than 37 years experience in the agricultural industry in South Africa. I have advanced knowledge, excellent practical experience and insight as an agricultural economist into the international and national macro-economic and agricultural economic developments which have a determined impact on the driving forces behind the profitability and sustainability of agricultural production, food security, value chains and bio-fuels development.

EDUCATION

- University of the Free State 1974 BSc-agric
- University of Pretoria 1978 MSc-agric

EMPLOYMENT RECORD/ PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Department of Agricultural Economics and Marketing.

Place: Pretoria/Bloemfontein, South Africa.

Job title: Agricultural Economist.

Period: January 1975 until September 1980.

Key responsibilities:

- Research on the production costs and profitability of the maize, wheat, oilseeds, dairy, red meat and wine industries to improve agricultural productivity and to maintain and ensure future food security in the country.
- Manage and support 30 farmer study groups in the Free State Province.
- Provide training to students in agricultural economics at the Glen Agricultural College near Bloemfontein.
- Develop a management information system for farmers.



Email: consultant@londonresearchinternational.com

www.LondonResearchInternational.com

• South African Agricultural Union (Agri SA).

Place: Pretoria, South Africa.

Job title: Senior Agricultural Economist Period: October 1980 until August 1984.

Key responsibilities:

- Render organisational and economical services to the grains and oilseeds industries on provincial and national level.
- o Administer and organise the national industry committees.
- Liaise with various government departments, marketing councils and other agricultural organisations.

• Verspreide Beleggings (Pty) Ltd.

Place Hennenman, South Africa.

Job title: Senior Agricultural Economist.

Period: September 1984 until March 1986.

Key responsibilities:

- Manage farming activities on 12 farms in the Eastern and North Western Free
 State.
- o Provide management information to the board of directors.

Kanhym Limited.

Place: Johannesburg, South Africa.

Job title: Group economist.

Period: April 1986 until November 1988.

Key responsibilities:

- Provide management information to the board of directors about developments in the red meat industry.
- Analyse and interpretation of production and marketing trends in the red meat industry.
- o Advise the board of directors on the economics of cattle feedlot production.

Grain South Africa (www.grainsa.co.za)

Place: Bothaville, South Africa.

Job title: Senior Economist and Deputy General



Email: consultant@londonresearchinternational.com

www.LondonResearchInternational.com

Manager: Research and Development.

Period: December 1988 until August 2006.

Key responsibilities:

- Manage the Inputs Working Group to improve the profitability and agricultural productivity of grain (maize, sorghum and wheat) and oilseeds (soybeans, sunflower seed and groundnuts) production for future food security in the country.
- Negotiate with the following organisations in the production input industries to enhance the supply of inputs to grain and oilseeds producers:
- Negotiate with various government departments and other institutions such as the
- Departments of Agriculture, Minerals and Energy, Trade and Industry, the National
- Treasury, South African Revenue Services and Statistics South Africa to develop, coordinate and harmonise food security policy recommendations.
- o Deliver presentations to branches and the congress of Grain SA.
- Publish articles in the monthly magazine of Grain SA and received the Koster

Appointed as Deputy General Manager: Research and Development from 1 July 2002.

Key responsibilities:

- Identify the most important priorities for the Division: Research and Development in order to improve the financial and economic welfare of grain producers and to improve agricultural productivity and food security.
- Manage and co-ordinate the research priorities and functions of the Division:
- Research and Development in respect of the inputs, production and marketing environment of the grains and oilseeds industries.
- Make various recommendations and presentations to Grain SA branches, regional conferences as well as to the Executive Committee and the congress of Grain SA in this regard.
- Communicate strategic information to the members of Grain SA by means of regional conferences, publications, electronic media, a TV program and the development of an internet website.



Email: consultant@londonresearchinternational.com

www.LondonResearchInternational.com

- Collaborate and negotiate with various governmental institutions, input suppliers, grain buyers, agricultural co-operatives and private sector agribusinesses to develop, coordinate and harmonise food security as well as grain and oilseeds value chains policy recommendations.
- Conduct various interviews with radio stations and television channels with regard to developments in the grain industry.
- Investigate the international production of biofuels and the development of a policy framework for the establishment of a biofuels industry in South Africa.
- Represent Grain SA on various working groups and forums as well as the Biodiesel Joint Implementation Committee and a consultative forum for the Task Team on the development of a Renewable Energy Strategy for South Africa.
- Make various presentations to governmental and private institutions in respect of the required policy and strategy for the development of a biofuels industry.
- Present a television programme on current affairs for farmers in the grain industry.

Biofuels Industry Development (Pty) Ltd.

Place: Bothaville/Pretoria, South Africa

Job title: Managing Director/Agriculture and

Biofuels Advisor.

Period: September 2006 to January 2009.

Key responsibilities:

Development and consultation with specific reference to the following developments and processes in the biofuels industry:

- Very involved in the developing of a biofuels industry in South Africa between 2005 and 2007 and represented Grain South Africa on various governmental working groups, more specific as far as a Biofuels Strategic Plan and Policy were concerned.
- Worked very closely with Sasol in the planning to build a 100,000 ton biodiesel from soybeans plant.
- Advisor to Ethanol Africa, a company of farmers who planned to build nine
 158 million litres per annum each bio-ethanol plants from 3 million tons



Email: consultant@londonresearchinternational.com www.LondonResearchInternational.com

London

maize in South

Africa, with specific reference to the following processes in the biofuels value chain:

- o Production input supply sourcing of good quality seed, fertiliser, crop protection chemicals, diesoline as well as machinery and implements at competitive prices.
- Production of feedstock production of maize, sorghum, wheat, barley, soybeans, sunflower, rapeseed and jatropha in a profitable, efficient and sustainable manner.
- Technology choice of technology provider, design and specifications of biofuel plants, conversion efficiencies of the fermentation and transesterification processes, performance guarantees and the cost of the technology.
- Government policy policy issues such as renewable energy targets, tax incentives, fuel level exemptions, mandatory regulations for biofuel blending, specifications and pricing, as well as the dependency on crude oil, food security, job creation and poverty reduction.
- Capital acquisition possible funding of projects by local commercial banks, international investors, as well as the producers of grains and oilseeds.
- Market development negotiations with government and the local oil industry about licensing, target blending, prices and specifications.
- Value-adding to co-products value-adding to dried distillers grains and solubles (DDGS) and oilcake as animal feed, manufacturing of human food, ethanol gel, wooden composites to replace wooden products and building materials, maize oil and protein extraction, as well as the purification of glycerol.
- Risk management managing climate, feedstock supply, technology, political, economic, market, as well as fraud and corruption risks.
- Economic feasibility and business plan submission and discussion with all relevant and interested role players.

Osprey Investments Ltd. Nigeria

Place: Yola, Adamawa State, Nigeria Job title: Senior Agricultural Consultant.



Email: consultant@londonresearchinternational.com www.LondonResearchInternational.com

Period: Short term consultancy from February to May 2009.

Key responsibilities:

- Serve as Senior Consultant on the Master Agriculture Plan assignment to address the problems of low agricultural productivity and food insecurity in Nigeria.
- Understand the objectives to be achieved under the Master Plan.
- o Discuss the Master Agriculture Plan with key stakeholders.
- o Liaise with project technical experts for developing the technical aspects of the Master Plan.
- o Contribute significantly to data needs, collection and analysis.
- Write significant portions of the State's Master Agriculture and Agro-Industry Plan.
- o Investigate the economic feasibility of food crops (rice, maize, sorghum, soybeans and groundnuts) and livestock (poultry and dairy) production as well as the processing of feed stocks to improve food security and nutrition in the commodity value chain.

PROFESSIONAL AFFILIATIONS

n/a

PUBLICATIONS

I have written more than 300 articles for popular magazines.

LANGUAGES

Afrikaans, English